W. R. "Bob" Poage State Legislative papers, Inclusive: 1923-1971, undated, Bulk: 1933-1936
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
W. R. "Bob" Poage State Legislative papers
Inclusive: 1923-1971, undated, Bulk: 1933-1936
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
1A
Poage, Bob
Poage, W. R. (William Robert), 1899 - 1987
11 document boxes
The W. R. “Bob” Poage State Legislative Papers house personal and political materials from Poage’s career in the Texas House of Representatives and the Texas Senate. Records include correspondence, legislation, news clippings, campaign materials, and other items.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
William Robert “Bob” Poage was born in Waco, Texas, on December 28, 1899. His early life was marked by moves to Albany, Texas, and Throckmorton County, Texas where his father owned or leased ranchlands. The Poages returned to Waco in 1913, and Bob graduated from Waco High School in 1918. He briefly attended Texas A&M, then joined the U.S. Navy at the end of World War I. Following the war, Poage enrolled at Baylor University. During the summer of 1919, Poage attended summer courses at the University of Texas where he was exposed to the state legislature. He returned to Baylor and completed his A.B. in Geology in 1921.
While attending Baylor, and for a short time after, Poage worked as a farmhand. Upon his return to Baylor in 1922, Poage taught geology and worked on his law degree. In 1923, Poage completed courses at the University of Colorado and obtained his LL.B from Baylor in 1924.
While still a law student, Poage ran for his first political office. He was elected to the Texas House of Representatives in 1924 and served in this capacity for four years while practicing law in Waco. Poage ran an unsuccessful campaign for State Senator against Edgar Witt in 1928. This led him back to Waco to practice law full-time.
Poage ran for re-election to the Texas Legislature in 1930 against Frank Baldwin and won the nomination. However, he declined this nomination to pursue the state Senate seat vacated by Edgar Witt upon his election as lieutenant governor. Poage won the vote in a special election and served the remainder of Witt’s term; he ran successfully for two additional terms serving as a Texas State Senator from 1931-1937.
In 1934, W. R. Poage ran for the U.S. House of Representatives for the first time amid declining approval for sitting Congressman O.H. Cross. Poage was unsuccessful in this bid. In 1936, he once again opposed Cross, this time defeating the Congressman. In 1937, Poage began his freshman campaign of a longstanding career in the U.S. House of Representatives.
Poage announced his retirement from Congress in 1977, and resigned December 1978. In 1979, the W. R. Poage Legislative Library, built in Poage’s honor, was opened on the Baylor University campus in Waco. The library housed Congressman Poage’s office throughout his retirement and continues to house his papers. W. R. Poage passed away in Temple, Texas, on January 3, 1987, and is buried in Waco's Oakwood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
The W. R. Poage State Legislative papers cover the period 1923-1971, however, the bulk of material is dated 1933-1936 during Poage’s tenure as Texas State Senator in the 43rd and 44th Legislatures.
Materials include correspondence, topical files, campaign files, and newspaper clippings. The papers are arranged chronologically and cover issues such as horse racing, alcohol taxation, and regulation of chain stores in the 13th State Senate district which included the counties of McLennan, Falls, Milam, and Limestone.
Arrangement
The Poage State papers were previously included as the first series of the W. R. “Bob” Poage papers. The W. R. "Bob" Poage State Legislative papers have been separated to create their own collection and better identify Poage’s work on the state level.
The State Legislative papers are organized into three series: I. Correspondence, II. Legislative, and III. Personal. The Personal series is further divided into three sub-series: I. Campaigns, II. Press, and III. Speeches and Programs.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1A. Acquired 1961-08-01
Related Resources
Items in related collections
W. R. "Bob" Poage Campaign papers, Inclusive: 1898-1997, undated, Bulk: 1936-1978
W. R. "Bob" Poage Texas Development papers, Inclusive: 1913-1979, undated, Bulk: 1946-1978
Related references
Poage, W. R. My First 85 Years. Waco: Texian Press, 1985.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Poage, W. R. (William Robert), 1899-1987.
Subjects (Organizations)
Texas. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Texas. Legislature. Senate.
Places
Texas -- Politics and government.
Subjects
Alcohol -- Taxation.; Chain stores -- Taxation -- Texas.; Legislators -- Texas -- Archives.; Political campaigns -- Texas.; Politicians -- Texas.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Records (Documents); Speeches.
- Correspondence, 1933-1971; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. Correspondence houses letters concerning appointments, job applications for state positions, and political matters within the 13th State Senate District of Texas (McLennan, Falls, Milam, and Limestone counties). The series has an inclusive date range of 1933-1971, however, most of the materials are dated 1933-1936 and are representative of the years Poage was in the Texas Senate. Materials are organized chronologically by year, then alphabetically within each year. The series is in good condition.
  - Acknowledgements, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alcohol, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anti-Trust Laws, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Applications, Appointments, Recommendations, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Banking, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bonds, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Budget, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Elections, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Events, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gas, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11A)
  - Highways, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Home Loans, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hospitals, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hunting, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Insurance, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Judiciary, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notary Public Appointments, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pension Laws, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Personal, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Railways, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Recommendations, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Redistricting, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sales Taxes, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 23A)
  - Telephone, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Texas, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Unemployment, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Veterans, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Acknowledgements, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Agriculture, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Alcohol, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Applications, Appointments, Recommendations, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Appropriations, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Banking, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baylor, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Brazos River Development, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cement Plant in Waco, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Education, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Elections, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Environment, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Events, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gas, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Higher Education, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Highways, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Horse Racing, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Judiciary, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Labor, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Law enforcement, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Legislature, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notary, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pari-mutuel, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Post Office, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Railways, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Senate Investigating Committee, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - State Parks, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - State Prisons, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Taxes, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Telephone, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Texas Centennial Committee, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 18A)
  - Texas Relief Commission, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Transportation, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Veterans, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Acknowledgements, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Agriculture, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Alcohol, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Applications, Appointments, Recommendations, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Appropriations, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Army, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Brazos River Conservation, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Cartoons/Drawings, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Chain Store Tax (1 of 2), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chain Store Tax (2 of 2), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Dispensary, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Driver License Law, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Education, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Elections, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Employment, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Events (1 of 2), 1935 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Events (2 of 2), 1935 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fee System, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Health Care, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Higher Education, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Highways, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - House Bill 100, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hughes, Sarah, Appointment as State District Judge, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hunting, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Insurance, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Labor, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Legislature (1 of 2), 1935 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Legislature (2 of 2), 1935 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Mental Health, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Nine-Juror Rule, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 19A)
  - Notary, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Oil and Gas, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Old Age Pension, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Petitions, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Prison, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Railways, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Security Act, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Social Security, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Tax (1 of 2), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Tax (2 of 2), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Texas Ports, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Texas River Board, Fraud Investigation, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 3A)
  - Texas Relief Commission, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Veterans, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Youth, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Acknowledgements (1 of 2), 1936 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Acknowledgements (2 of 2), 1936 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Agriculture, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Applications, Appointments, Recommendations, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Banking, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Child Labor, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Driver’s License, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Education, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Elections, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Electrification, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Employment, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Events, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Health, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Highways, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hospital, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Insurance, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Legislation, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mental Health, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Nominations, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Notary, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Old Age Pensions (1 of 2), 1936 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Old Age Pensions (2 of 2), 1936 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Schools, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - School for the Blind, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Social Security Act, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Tax, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Texas Centennial Celebration, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Veterans, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Legislation, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Veterans, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Legislation, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Insurance, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Legislation, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Texas State Journal, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Legislative, 1925-1936, undated; 2
  Series II. Legislative covers a wide range of topics including horse racing, alcohol taxation, and the regulation of chain stores. Also included are state responses to early New Deal programs. This series is arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically within each year. Most of the materials are in good condition.
  - Civil Court Cases Bill, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Fair Associations and Governing State Board, House Bill #157, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Rate-Making Bodies and Injunctions, Senate Bill #6, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Taxes, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - General, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - General, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Motor Bus Rules and Regulations Adopted by the Railroad Commission of Texas, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Laws of States Fixing the Number of Jurors, 1929 January (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Anti-Technicality Bills, circa 1930's (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Insurance, 1931 September 10 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - General, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Sales Taxes, 1932, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - General, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Alcohol, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Anti-Trust Laws, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - County Boundaries and Alterations, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Court Jurisdiction, McLennan County, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Dove and Quail Season, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Fire Insurance Appraisal Bill, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Guarantee Deposit Bill State Banks, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Insurance, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Medical Practice Act, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Mineral Rights Recovery, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Motor Carrier Law and Rules and Regulations Adopted by the Railroad Commission of Texas, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Oil, 1933-1936 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Propagation of Wild Game Funds, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Public School Funding, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Railroads, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Redefining “Loan Broker”, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Regulating Non-Intoxicating Beer, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Regulatory, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Salaries, Road Supervisor, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Schools, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Senate Simple Resolutions, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sherriff as Assessor and Collector of Taxes, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Taxes, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Tax on Malt, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Workmen’s Compensation Amendment, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - General, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Alcohol Regulation, Senate Bill #1, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Appropriations, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Axtell High School, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Chain Store Investigation, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Chain Store Tax (1 of 2), 1935 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Chain Store Tax (2 of 2), 1935 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Claims Against State, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Contingencies, Legislator/Attorney, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Cotton, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Driver’s Licensing, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Natural Resources Taxes (1 of 3), 1935 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Natural Resources Taxes (2 of 3), 1935 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Natural Resources Taxes (3 of 3), 1935 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Omnibus Tax Bill, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Poll Tax Exemptions, House Bill #95, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Railroads, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Report on Insurance Department Made to Senate Investigating Committee, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Roads, Bell County, 1935, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Social Security, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Taxes, Delinquent, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Texas Memorial Museum, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Utility Tax, House Bill #21, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - General, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Amendments to Soil Conservation and Domestic Allotment Act, Senate Bill #3780, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Injunctions, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Insurance Investigation Report, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Natural Resources Tax, House Bill #8, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Natural Resources Tax, 1936-1937 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Rural Representation in the Legislature, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Sales Tax, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Senate Investigating Committee, Report from Tom Deberry, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Social Security, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Personal, 1923-1936, undated; 3
  Series III. Personal is dated 1923-1936, and divided into three subseries: Campaigns, Press, and Speeches and Programs.
  The Campaigns subseries includes itineraries, speeches, and materials from Congressman Bob Poage’s unsuccessful run for the U.S. House of Representatives against O.H. Cross in 1934, as well as his successful campaign against Cross in 1936.
  The Press subseries includes news clippings about Poage and his campaigns as well as newsletters printed while he was in state office.
  The Speeches and Programs subseries includes one speech by Poage and several given to him by others. The two programs are from the 1917 and 1919 Texas Gubernatorial Inaugural Balls.
  The materials in this series are arranged in chronological order and are in good condition.
  - Campaigns, 1923-1936; 1
    - McLennan County Roadmap, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Advisement, Announcement Opposition and Support, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Appearances, Opposition and Support, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Expenses, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Itinerary and Advisements, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Speeches, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Congressional Race Speculation, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Advertisements, Speeches, and Support, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Appearances and Support (1 of 3), 1936 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Appearances and Support (2 of 3), 1936 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Appearances and Support (3 of 3), 1936 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Congressional Campaign, Announcement and Support, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Speeches, O.H. Cross, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Press, 1932-1936; 2
    - News Clippings, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - News Clippings, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - News Clippings, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - News Clippings, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Newsletters, State Senate, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - News Clippings, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Newsletters, State Senate, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Speeches and Programs, 1934-1936, undated; 3
    - Address of Honorable Nelson Phillips before Judiciary Committee of the Senate in 1909 in Opposition to Bill to Abolish Unanimity of Jury Verdicts, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Navy Day Speech by Bob Poage, circa 1934 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - "The Supreme Court of the United States, the Constitution, and its Amendments" by Honorable William E. Masterson, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Texas Gubernatorial Inaugural Ball Programs, 1917-1919 (Box 11, Folder 15)